Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we explore the power
of the mighty mushroom.
Did you know that it may
be even more important
to include mushrooms (or tempeh)
in our diet as we age?
Here’s our first story.
Of more than a hundred compounds
measured in the bloodstreams
of thousands of individuals,
the one most associated with the lowest
rates of disease and death
was ergothioneine.
Higher blood levels
were associated with lower risk
of heart disease, stroke, and death
from all causes put together
over a period of more than 20 years.
Ergothioneine is an unusual amino acid.
Although it was discovered
more than a century ago,
it was ignored until recently,
when researchers found
that humans have a highly specific
transporter protein in our bodies
specifically designed to pull ergothioneine
out of food and into body tissue.
It’s even upregulated
right before meal times.
This suggests that ergothioneine plays
an important physiological role.
But what? Our first clue
was the tissue distribution.
Ergothioneine concentrates
in parts of your body
where there are lots of free radicals—
the lens of your eye and your liver,
for example, as well as sensitive tissues
such as bone marrow and semen.
Researchers found it acts
as a cytoprotectant—a cell protector.
Depriving human cells
of ergothioneine
leads to accelerated
DNA damage and cell death.
Because we can only get it in food,
and there’s toxicity
associated with its depletion,
Johns Hopkins University
researchers concluded
that ergothioneine
“may represent a new vitamin.”
If it were classified as such,
that would make it the first new vitamin
since the last new vitamin, B12,
was isolated back in 1948.
However, traditional vitamins
are characterized
by the manifestation of an overt
dietary deficiency disease
within a short time frame,
and no specific deficiency disease
has yet been identified.
But perhaps deﬁciency diseases
are staring us in the face.
Low blood levels of ergothioneine
are correlated with increased risk
of frailty, cardiovascular disease,
cognitive impairment,
dementia, and Parkinson’s disease.
To describe nutrients that may not
necessarily be essential for life
but may be essential
for long-term health,
the famous biochemist Bruce Ames
coined the term “longevity vitamin”
and identified ergothioneine
as a putative candidate.
What are the best dietary sources?
It’s not made by plants or animals;
only fungi like mushrooms
and certain soil bacteria.
Plants can suck some up from the soil,
and animals who eat the plants
can similarly benefit,
but the highest levels by far
have been reported in mushrooms.
Excessive tillage of the soil,
which is a common practice
in modern agriculture,
can disrupt the mycelial network,
the fungi filaments
that pass ergothioneine along
to the roots of crops,
leaving mushrooms and tempeh—
a fungi-fermented soybean cake—
as the only concentrated
dietary sources.
This is on a dry weight basis, though,
and mushrooms are like 90 percent water;
so, if you change this
to prepared wet weight,
tempeh does even better on more
of a per serving basis.
As mushrooms go, shiitake may have
comparable levels to oyster mushrooms,
about five times more
than white button mushrooms,
but may also be five times as expensive—
unless you grow your own.
Oyster mushrooms can grow
in less than two weeks
with just-add-water kits.
Here’s a pic
from my own personal stash.
Porcinis may lead the pack, though,
which could explain why Italians
average more than four times
the average ergothioneine intake
of Americans.
But even just eating a cup a day
of plain white button mushrooms
can double ergothioneine
concentrations in the blood.
Yes, ergothioneine is associated
with reduced mortality,
but it was also the blood metabolite
most strongly connected
to a “health conscious food pattern;”
so, it could just have just been a proxy
for healthier eating.
And look, correlation
doesn’t mean causation.
Instead of low ergothioneine levels
leading to disease,
maybe disease somehow leads
to lower ergothioneine levels?
What evidence do we have that we should
go out of our way to eat mushrooms?
Well, mushrooms can reduce atherosclerosis
in butterfat-fed mice,
and fruit flies fed
a 1 percent oyster mushroom diet
did show a slight but significant
survival advantage.
And we suspect it’s the ergothioneine,
since you can give it straight
and still get a life-extension eﬀect.
But what evidence do we have in people?
Well, mushroom consumption
is associated with a lower risk of cancer,
driven mainly by lower
breast cancer rates,
and mushroom consumption
is associated with a lower risk
of dying prematurely
from all causes put together.
I have covered interventional trials
showing, for example,
that eating just a few mushrooms
a day can improve immune function,
but ergothioneine may be an
underrecognized dietary micronutrient
for healthy aging in other ways as well.
Dietary ergothioneine is known
to cross the blood-brain barrier,
since it can be found
in human cerebrospinal fluid
and post-mortem brain samples.
Perhaps this is why a study in Singapore
found that those who consumed
more than two servings
of mushrooms a week
had less than half the odds of suffering
from mild cognitive impairment,
compared to less than once a week.
And a study
of more than 10,000 Japanese elders
found that three or more times
a week mushroom eaters
had a significantly lower risk
of developing dementia
over a period of about six years.
With cross-sectional studies
correlating mushroom consumption
with better brain function,
researchers decided to put it to the test
using lion’s mane mushroom,
which is especially popular
in traditional Chinese medicine.
Randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials on people
with normal cognitive function,
on people with mild cognitive impairment,
and on those with early-stage
Alzheimer’s disease
did find small cognitive or functional
improvements after months
of a third to a full teaspoon
of powdered lion’s mane mushroom a day
compared to placebo.
Interestingly, blood ergothioneine levels
appear to decline after about age 60,
and this decline is tied
to both cognitive decline and frailty.
And this does not appear to be due
to declining mushroom intake with age;
so, perhaps the function
of the ergothioneine transporter
at the blood-brain barrier
declines with age,
potentially making mushroom intake
all the more beneficial as we grow older.
So, if I was to create
a Dr. Greger’s Baker’s Dozen,
I would probably add mushrooms
to the list.
In our next story,
we look at the power of medicinal
mushrooms for cancer survival.
Can mushrooms be medicinal?
Mushroom-based products
make up a sizable chunk of the
$50 billion supplement market.
This profitable trade provides a powerful
incentive for companies to test
the credulity of their customers, and
sadly, unsupported assertions
have come to define the
medical mushroom business.
For example, companies that market herbal
medicines exploit references to studies
on mice to promote their
mushroom capsules
for treating all kinds of ailments,
but if you haven't noticed,
we're not mice.
I mean, it wouldn't be surprising if
mushrooms had some potent properties.
After all, fungi are where
we got a bunch of drugs,
not the least of which, penicillin.
And also a cholesterol-lowering
drug, lovastatin,
and the powerful immunosuppressant
drug, cyclosporin.
Still don't think a little mushroom
can have pharmacological effects?
Don't forget they can produce some
of our most powerful poisons.
Some kind of look the part, like
the toxic Carolina false morel,
all toadstooly and such, but others
have more of an angelic look,
indeed literally called the
Destroying Angel—that's its name—
and as little as a teaspoon can
cause a painful, lingering death.
So anyway, we should have respect
for the pharmacological potential
of mushrooms, but what can
they do that's good for us?
Well, consuming shiitake mushrooms
daily improves human immunity.
Giving people just one or two
dried shiitake mushrooms a day—
about the weight equivalent of five
to ten fresh ones—for four weeks
resulted in an increase in proliferation
of gamma-delta T lymphocytes
and doubled the proliferation
of natural killer cells.
Gamma-delta cells act as a first
line of immunological defense,
and even better,
natural killer cells kill cancer,
and the shiitake did all this while
lowering markers of systemic inflammation.
Oyster mushroom extracts don't seem
to work as well, but what we care about
is if mushrooms can actually
affect cancer outcomes.
Shiitakes haven't been tried yet,
but reishi mushrooms have,
after being used as a cancer treatment
throughout Asia for centuries.
Reishi mushroom for cancer treatment:
what does the science say?
A meta-analysis of five randomized
controlled trials showed that patients
who had been given reishi mushroom
supplements along with chemo and
radiation were more likely to
respond positively compared
to just chemo and radiation alone.
Now although adding a reishi mushroom
extract improved tumor response rates,
the data failed to demonstrate
a significant effect on tumor shrinkage
when the mushrooms were used alone.
So they aren't recommended
as a single treatment,
but rather an adjunct treatment
for patients with advanced cancer.
Now response rate just
means the tumor shrinks.
What we care about is whether
or not it actually improves
survival or quality of life. And
we don't have convincing data
suggesting reishi mushroom
products improve survival.
But those randomized to
reishi were found to have
a relatively better quality of life, so
that's a win as far as I'm concerned.
What about other mushrooms?
Although whole shiitake mushrooms
haven't been tested yet,
there's a compound that's extracted
from shiitakes called lentinan,
which is said to have
completely inhibited the growth
of a certain kind of sarcoma in mice.
But in actuality it only worked
in one single strain of mice
and failed in nine others.
So are we more like the 90% of
mouse strains in which it didn't work?
We need human trials,
and we finally got them.
There are data on nearly 10,000
cancer patients who have been treated
with the shiitake mushroom extract
injected right into their veins.
What did the researchers find?
There is a compound called lentinan,
extracted from shiitake mushrooms.
To get about an ounce you have to
distill around 400 pounds of shiitakes.
That's like 2,000 cups of mushrooms.
But then you can inject the compound into
cancer patients and see what happens.
The pooled response from a dozen
small clinical trials found that
the objective response rate
was significantly improved
when lentinan was added to
chemotherapy regimens for lung cancer.
"Objective response rate"
means like tumor shrinkage,
but what we really care about
is survival and quality of life.
Does it actually make cancer patients
live any longer or any better?
Well, those in the lentinan group
suffered less chemo-related toxicity
to their gut and bone marrow,
so that alone might be
reason enough to use it.
But what about improving survival?
I was excited to see that lentinan
evidently could
significantly improve survival rates
for a type of leukemia. And here it is.
Adding lentinan increased average
survival and reduced cachexia—
which is like cancer-associated muscle
wasting—and improved cage-side health.
Wait, what? How...
Damn it.
This was improved survival
for brown Norwegian rats.
So that so-called clinical benefit
only applies if you're a veterinarian.
A compilation of 17 actual human
clinical studies did find improvements
in one-year survival in
advanced cancer patients,
but no significant difference in the
likelihood of living out to two years.
Even the compilations of studies
that purport that lentinan offers a
significant advantage in terms of survival
are talking about statistical significance.
Lentinan improved survival
by an average of 25 days.
Now, 25 days is 25 days, but we should
evaluate claims made by companies
about the miraculous properties of
medicinal mushrooms very critically.
Lentinan has to be
injected intravenously.
What about mushroom extract
supplements you can just take yourself?
Shiitake mushroom extract is available
through the Internet for the treatment
of prostate cancer for
approximately $300 a month,
so it's got to be good, right?
Men who regularly eat mushrooms
do seem to be at lower risk
for getting prostate cancer,
and not apparently just because
they eat less meat or more fruits
and vegetables in general. So why not
give a shiitake mushroom extract a try?
Because it doesn't work—ineffective in
the treatment of clinical prostate cancer.
The results demonstrate that
complementary and alternative
medicine claims can actually be
put to the test. What a concept!
Maybe it should be mandatory before
patients spend large sums of money
on unproven treatments, or in
this case, a disproven treatment.
What about God's mushroom, also
known as the Mushroom of Life
or reishi mushrooms?
Conclusions: no significant
anticancer effects were found,
not even a single partial response.
Maybe we're overthinking it?
Plain white button mushroom
extracts can kill off prostate
cancer cells,
at least in a petri dish,
but so could the fancy God's mushroom,
but that didn't end up working in people.
You don't know if plain white
button mushrooms work or not
until you put it to the test.
What I like about this study is that
the researchers didn't use
a proprietary extract. They just
used regular whole mushrooms,
dried and powdered—
the equivalent of a half cup
to a cup and a half of fresh white
button mushrooms a day—
in other words, a totally doable amount.
They gave them to men
with biochemically recurrent
prostate cancer.
What that means is the men had already
gotten a prostatectomy or radiation
in an attempt to cut or burn out all the
cancer, but now it's back and growing,
as evidenced by a rise in PSA levels, an
indicator of prostate cancer progression.
Of the 26 patients who got
the button mushroom powder,
four appeared to respond,
meaning they got a drop
in PSA levels by more than
50% after starting the 'shrooms.
Now in the majority of cases,
the PSA levels continued to rise,
not dipping at all.
But even if there is only a 1 in 18
chance you'll be like these two
with a prolonged complete
response that continues to date,
we're not talking about weighing the
risks of some toxic chemotherapy
for the small chance of benefit; just
eating some inexpensive, easy, tasty,
plain white mushrooms every day.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.